Okay, today’s דף *daf* is מ"ג *Mem Gimmel*, 43, we pick up
on מ"ב עמוד ב' *Mem Bet Amud Bet*. And we are, the
line starts with the word השולח *Hasholeach*. And we have now wrapped
up the discussion about where you learn the basic principle of שליחות
shelichus. *shelichus* from: from תרומה Trumah *terumah*, from קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin* and
גיטין *Gittin*, from קרבנות *korbanos*. And now we’re going to deal with
some exceptions to the rule, particularly the concept of שליח לדבר עבירה
shliach ledvar aveirah. *shaliach lidvar aveira*. So again מ"ב עמוד ב' *Mem
Bet Amud Bet*, והדתנן השולח *vehadetnan Hasholeach*. Line starts with the word
השולח *Hasholeach* halfway down. השולח את הבעירה ביד חרש שוטה וקטן *Hasholeach
es habeeirah beyad cheresh shoteh vekatan*. If somebody sends a torch, a
fire, in the hands of a חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh vekatan*,
a deaf-mute, a שוטה *shoteh* is somebody who has a psychiatric illness
and doesn’t think clearly like somebody maybe schizophrenic who doesn't process reality
properly, and a קטן *katan*, a minor—all these people are not considered
to be responsible for their actions. חרש *cheresh* is a whole separate
discussion, the status nowadays. פטור patur, מדיני אדם וחייב מדיני שמים *potur
midinei adam vechayav midinei shamayim*. So they’re exempt, they’re not responsible for
their actions, and the one who sent them is exempt from the
laws
of human laws but has liability to Heaven because they obviously caused
a conflagration and property to be destroyed. Okay, but שילח ביד פיקח,
פיקח חייב chayav *shillach beyad pikeach, pikeach chayav*. If it was sent
in the hand of somebody who is an adult and is of
his right mind, פיקח חייב chayav *pikeach chayav*. Then the adult who
is—did the burning is חייב chayav *chayav*, and the one who sent
him is exempt. This is like the person who organizes and orchestrates
the RICO laws and all of that; the הלכה halacha *halacha* is
that from a הלכה *halacha* point of view, that person who’s the
manipulator and the organizer, they are not directly responsible, they’re not the
one who did it, it’s only the person who actually lit the
flame that did it. But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to
understand why are you not חייב chayav. *chayav* from the perspective of
שליחות shlichus, *shelichus*. ואמאי, נימא שליח shliach של אדם כמותו *vamai, neima
sheliach shel adam kemoso*? Why not, why don’t we say that a
person’s שליח shliach *shaliach* is like them? And here, you know, it
could be from a perspective of criminal, but also could be a
perspective of torts and civil, right? So why don’t I bear the
liability if I had my שליח shliach, *shaliach* do it? Now, of
course you could say that שליחות shlichus. *shelichus* does not mean it’s
my physical action, like I also can’t make a שליח shaliach *shaliach*
to do a מצוה *mitzvah* for me. שליחות shlichus *shelichus* is more
about giving somebody my authority that’s invested in me. Lighting a fire
is not authority, right? So there’s a—it’s interesting that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* sort of sees this as part of the conversation,
but let’s see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is. שאני התם
דאין שליח לדבר עבירה shliach ledvar aveirah *shani hasam de'ein shaliach lidvar
aveira*. There it’s different that there is no שליח shliach *shaliach* for
a matter of sin. Why? So if you have somebody do something
that is a transgression, that cannot be attributed back to you, the
משלח meshalei'ach *meshaleach*. Why? דאמרינן דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעין
divrei harav vedivrei hatalmid divrei mi shomin, *damrinan divrei harav vedivrei hatalmid
divrei mi shome'in*? Because we say, between the words of the Master
and the words of the student, whose words do you listen to?
Meaning you say to the שליח shaliach, *shaliach*, okay, I’m a human
being, but why did you listen to me? You should be listening
to God, and God told you that you’re not allowed to do
it. Now, of course we all know that some—very often we’re more
influenced by humans than by God in our fear of God, but
ideally the point is it’s not my responsibility, you can’t say I
made you do it. Ultimately, if you violated the law, you are
responsible for your own choices, and therefore it is your sin, it’s
not my sin and your liability and not my liability. Again, it’s
interesting that because you might have thought שליחות shlichus *shelichus* is just
irrelevant here because it’s about whose physical act is it, not who
is given legal authority. But this is an important principle across the
board: דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד divrei harav vedivrei hatalmid. דברי מי שומעין
*divrei harav vedivrei hatalmid divrei mi shome'in*. It’s actually interesting whether this
would apply if the שליח shaliach *shaliach* was not aware that it
was a sin. Let’s say he thought he was—the person asked him
to, I don’t know,
tear, here’s my car, I want you to bring it to the
dump and I want you to get it to get pulverized, and
he didn’t realize that it was somebody else’s car, right? So then
maybe actually the משלח meshaleach *meshaleach* would be חייב chayav, *chayav* because
the שליח shaliach, *shaliach* didn’t have a reason not to believe, you
know, not to do it. All right, so
let’s take—let’s continue in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. והדתניא *vehad'tanya*, that which
we taught in the ברייתא Baraita, *beraita*, שליח shaliach שלא עשה שליחותו
שליח shaliach מעל, עשה שליחותו בעל הבית baal habayis מעל *shaliach shelo
asah shelichuso shaliach ma'al, asah shelichuso ba'al habayis ma'al*. So there’s a
principle that if you tell somebody—מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah* is if you accidentally
spend הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* money. So you have a person, you have
money in it and you think it’s not הקדש *hekdesh* money, and
you tell your שליח shaliach *shaliach* to go ahead and to buy
you some, you know, vegetables in the supermarket for it. So if
he went ahead and he bought the wrong thing, instead of buying
vegetables he bought, I don’t know, apples, so then then he’s not
operating because of your, because, you know, the mission you sent him
on, he’s operating on his own, so therefore he was the one
that misspent the הקדש *hekdesh* money and he did מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah*.
שלא עשה שליחותו שליח shaliach מעל, עשה שליחותו בעל הבית baal habayis
מעל *shelo asah shelichuso shaliach ma'al, asah shelichuso ba'al habayis ma'al*. But
if he actually bought the vegetables and he was operating based on
what I told him, then it’s my sin and I did מעילה
Me'ilah *me'ilah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, כי עשה שליחותו דבעל
הבית, בעל הבית מי מעל *ki asah shelichuso deba'al habayis, ba'al habayis
mi ma'al*? So look, how do we understand that? Why does the
בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* do מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah* when he listened to
him? ואמאי, נימא אין שליח לדבר עבירה ein shliach ledvar aveirah *vamai,
neima ein shaliach lidvar aveira*? We should say there’s no שליח shaliach
*shaliach* for a matter of sin. Now, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* here asks
because I said the whole מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*... is only when it's
by שוגג. shogeg, So if it's by שוגג, shogeg maybe there will
be a שליח לדבר עבירה. shliach ledvar aveirah So תוספות sort of
deals with that, but it does raise an interesting question whether the
real principle is דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד divrei harav v'divrei hatalmid דברי
מי שומעין, that the שליח shaliach, in this particular case should have
known better, or is it a different principle that you're only like
חייב chayav. for an עבירה aveirah if you do it yourself and
you know just fundamentally there's no שליח לדבר עבירה shliach ledvar aveirah
even if the שליח shaliach didn't have a reason not to do
it. Okay, but anyway but the גמרא Gemara has not gone into
that question of שוגג shogeg or מזיד. maysid. גמרא Gemara says אין
שליח לדבר עבירה ein shaliach lidvar aveirah, should mean that it's not
the בעל הבית's sin. Why is it the בעל הבית's sin? שאני
מעילה דילף חטא חטא מתרומה. shani Me'ilah diyalaf cheit cheit miTrumah. No,
there's a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah it says by חטא cheit by
תרומה Trumah and חטא cheit by מעילה me'ilah, and we already learned
תרומה Trumah is one of the sources for the idea of שליחות.
shlichus, So מה תרומה משכחת שליח אף מעילה משכחת שליח. mah Trumah
mishvach shliach af Me'ilah mishvach shliach. The same way by תרומה you
make a שליח, shaliach, when it comes to misspending of הקדש money,
if it came through שליחות, shlichus it gets back to you the
משלח meshaleach and you are liable for that sin. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says ונילף מינה, veneilaf minah, so why doesn't that serve
as a paradigm and why don't we learn from that to apply
to all other cases?
משום דהוי מעילה ושליחות יד שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין mishum dehavei Me'ilah veshlichus yad shnei kesuvin habayim
ke'echad vechol shnei kesuvin habayim ke'echad ein melamdin because there's another case
where there's a principle of שליח לדבר עבירה shliach ledvar aveirah, if
you're watching a פיקדון, pikadon, you know somebody's object and you're a
שומר shomer on it, you're and and
and you go ahead and you take it and use it for
yourself, right? You were supposed to be watching this guy's car and
instead you decided to drive it for a spin. So once you
are שליח יד, sholei'ach yad, you know you cast your hand against
it, then you become liable for any damage that occurs to it.
Now, what if it's not you did it? What if you had
somebody and sent somebody to go ahead and use it? So that
is a principle that that also makes you liable. So here's another
example where there is a שליח לדבר עבירה shliach ledvar aveirah because
you're not allowed to, it's not your property.
So by the way both notice that both the מעילה me'ilah, case
and this case, it is about something you're not supposed to do,
but there's also a question here not just about sin but about
liability,
so it's interesting the way those two intersect and those are in
the you know these categories where there is an element of שליחות.
Okay, but because these two are exceptions, the principle is if there
was a rule of שליח לדבר עבירה, shliach ledvar aveirah, the תורה
Torah wouldn't have written it in two places, it only would have
been in one. So if it writes it in two places, שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין, shnei kesuvin habayim ke'echad ein melamdin, that
teaches you that it's an exception and that it's not a rule.
Okay, שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. shnei kesuvin habayim ke'echad ein
melamdin. מעילה הא דאמרן, Me'ilah hadamran, מעילה me'ilah, likely said, and שליחות
יד מאי? shlichus yad mai? What's the case of שליחות יד? shlichus
yad? דתניא, ditanya, we learn in a ברייתא, baraita, על כל דבר
פשע, al kol devar pesha, on any matter of sin that you
say כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh, you know that you take
an oath אשר לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו, asher lo shalach yado
bimleches reiehu, that you did not do שליחות יד, shlichus yad, you
did not take it and use it for yourself. So בית שמאי
אומרים לחייב על המחשבה כמעשה, Beis Shammai omrim lechayav al hamachshavah kema'aseh,
על כל דבר פשע al kol devar pesha means anything and the
word דבר, davar, דיבור, dibbur, even if you say you want to
take it for yourself, you're planning on it or thinking about it,
that makes you liable. ובית הלל אומרים, uBeis Hillel omrim, בית הלל
Beis Hillel says no, אינו חייב עד שישלח בו יד. eino chayav
ad sheyishlach bo yad. You have to do it directly, you actually
have to use it. שנאמר אם לא שלח ידו, shene'emar im lo
shalach yado, in the end the פסוק pasuk says it's about being
שלח יד. sholei'ach yad. Okay, אמרו בית שמאי לבית הלל, amru Beis
Shammai leBeis Hillel, ולא נאמר על כל דבר פשע, velo neemar al
kol devar pesha, on any matter, so how can you say only
when you're actually
שלח יד? sholei'ach yad? אמרו להם בית הלל לבית שמאי, amru lahem
Beis Hillel leBeis Shammai, ולא נאמר אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו,
velo neemar im lo shalach yado bimleches reiehu, no, I have a
פסוק pasuk that says you have to be שלח יד. sholei'ach yad.
So אמרו בית שמאי לבית הלל, amru Beis Shammai leBeis Hillel, אם
כן על כל דבר פשע למה לי? im kein al kol devar
pesha lamah li? Okay, I get it, I get why you want
to be שלח יד sholei'ach yad literally, but still what do you
do with על כל דבר פשע? al kol devar pesha? שיכול אין
לי אלא הוא, sheyachol ein li ela hu, so now we're going
to get the answer. אלא הוא אמרו לעבדו ושלוחו מנין? ela hu
amru leavdo ushlucho minayin? So this now בית הלל Beis Hillel answering,
because על כל דבר פשע al kol devar pesha says even if
it's דבר, davar, דיבור, dibbur, but not an expression of desire but
a דיבור dibbur because you told somebody to do it. How do
you know if you told your slave or you told your your
agent to go ahead and to, you know, make use of it?
So מנין תלמוד לומר על כל דבר פשע. minayin talmud lomar al
kol devar pesha. Okay, so for בית הלל Beis Hillel you see
that there's an idea of שליח לדבר עבירה shliach l'dvar aveirah. for
שליחות יד shlichus yad and מעילה me'ilah. and therefore those are the
exceptions not the rule. So the גמרא Gemara. continues הני לבית הלל
אלא לבית שמאי דמוקמי לה להאי קרא במחשבה כמעשה נילף מינה. hani
lBeis Hillel ela lBeis Shammai dimokmi lah lhai kra bemachshavah kema'aseh neilaf
minah. Okay, that's good for בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says that, you know, it's not about שליחות at all,
there's just thought is enough to make you liable. So for him
you only have one פסוק pasuk by שליח לדבר עבירה, shaliach lidvar
aveira מעילה, me'ilah so maybe that's the rule, not the exception? No,
there's another case. משום דהוי מעילה וטביחה ומכירה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. mishum dehavei Me'ilah utvichah umechira
shnei kesuvin habayim ke'echad vechol shnei kesuvin habayim ke'echad ein melamdin. There's
another case where שליחות applies per דבר עבירה. devar aveirah. If you
are a גנב gannav and you burgle something and then you slaughter
it or sell it, then it's a sheep or an ox, you're
חייב chayav four or five times, okay, to pay back. And we're
going to learn now that that's even if you have somebody else
slaughter it for you. Again, notice it's a דבר עבירה devar aveirah
but we're also dealing with civil liability. Anyway, so because those are
two cases where you're חייב chayav for שליחות בדבר עבירה, shlichus bidvar
aveirah, those are the exceptions and not the rule. וחוץ מתרי הני
דאמרינן דמהכי לא ילפינן. vechutz mitrei hanei damrinan demai hach lo yalfinan.
אי להא דאמרן, ee leha deamran, מי לא mi lo we said?
טביחה ומכירה מאי היא, tevicha umchira mai hee, what is it? אמר
קרא amar kra וטבחו או מכרו, utvacho o mechoro, you shall slaughter
it or sell it. מה מכירה על ידי אחר אף טביחה על
ידי אחר. mah mechira al yedei acher af tevicha al yedei acher.
The same way you have to sell, there's gotta be another party
involved, the buyer, so slaughtering also is when there's even if there's
another party involved, even if you have somebody slaughter it for you,
you're still going to be חייב. chayav דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא devei
Rabbi Yishmael tana או o לרבות את השליח. lerabos es hashaliach. דבי
רבי ישמעאל devei Rabbi Yishmael learns it out from a different פסוק.
pasuk. או טבחו או מכרו. o utvacho o mechoro. The או o
comes to include even if a שליח shaliach does it. דבי חזקיה
תנא devei Chizkiyah tana תחת. tachas. You pay four צאן tzon תחת
tachas and five תחת. tachas. So תחת tachas tells you לרבות את
השליח. lerabos es hashaliach. Okay, so we have two exceptions, מעילה, me'ilah,
maybe שליחות יד, shlichus yad, and טביחה ומכירה. tevicha umchira. Two to
three exceptions, and therefore those are the exceptions and those are not
the rules. So גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד אין מלמדין. haniucha leman de'amar shenei kesuvim habaim k'echad ein melamdin.
That's if when you say if they're two times we treat them
as exceptions and not rules. אלא למאן דאמר מלמדין. ela leman de'amar
melamdin. But some people say that even if it says it twice
we still treat it as a rule. You'll need it to be
three times to say they're exceptions, 'cause then really if it was
a rule just say it once or twice. So מאי איכא למימר,
mai ika l'meimar, what can you say? Now again, for בית הלל
Beis Hillel it's fine. You have three times: מעילה, me'ilah, what do
you call it? מעילה, me'ilah
שליחות יד, shlichus yad, and טביחה ומכירה. tevicha umchira. For בית שמאי
Beis Shammai you only have two times. So the גמרא Gemara says
גלי רחמנא בשחוטי חוץ gali Rachmana bishchutei chutz דם יחשב לאיש ההוא
דם שפך. dam yeichashev la'ish hahu dam shafach. No, 'cause we have
another place where the תורה Torah tells you it's only if you
do it yourself. Another place of שחיטה, shechitah, not שחט-ing shachat somebody
that you burgled, but slaughtering a קרבן korban outside of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And it says האיש ההוא, ha'ish hahu, that man
who did it is חייב, chayav, not if you had somebody do
it for you. So that ההוא hahu is telling you that that
is the rule. Only the doer himself is the one who is
חייב. chayav. דם יחשב לאיש ההוא דם שפך. dam yeichashev la'ish hahu
dam shafach. הוא ולא שלוחו. hu velo shlucho. Only he himself. Okay,
so you have a specific פסוק pasuk and it only says it
once. So it's telling you once, that's actually telling you that that
is the principle, 'cause we already know logically we want to say
that, because דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד. divrei harav v'divrei hatalmid. So that's
telling you that's the principle and the other cases are the exception.
So the גמרא Gemara says אשכחן גבי שחוטי חוץ בכל התורה כולה
מנלן? ashkachan gabei shchutei chutz bechol hatorah kullah minalan? Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara still isn't yet satisfied. Maybe it's limited to שחוטי חוץ.
shchutei chutz. How do we know that this is the rule, that
only the doer himself? דיליף משחוטי חוץ. deyalif mishchutei chutz. Okay, שחוטי
חוץ shchutei chutz is the paradigm. One minute, says the גמרא. Gemara
אדרבה משחוטי חוץ ניליף מהנך? adarabba mishchutei chutz neilif mehanach? So maybe
we should learn out from, you know, these other two: טביחה ומכירה
tevicha umchira and מעילה. me'ila Alright, maybe we shouldn't look at those
as exceptions. Again, what makes you give preference to שחוטי חוץ shchutei
chutz as the rule? הדר כתב רחמנא ונכרת האיש ההוא. hadar kasav
Rachmana venichras ha'ish hahu. It tells you again, that man gets כרת.
kares. So it says ההוא hahu twice. So אם אינו ענין לגופו
im einu inyan legufo if that extra ההוא hahu is telling, is
not telling you that just שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz only the doer,
but תנהו ענין לכל התורה כולה. tanehu inyan lechol hatorah kullah. The
extra one is extra and it's not about a specific case, so
it's telling you this is the general rule: only the doer. And
טביחה ומכירה tevicha umchira and מעילה are the exceptions. Fine. So that's
how we know the principle אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach lidvar
aveirah. though there are some exceptions particularly when they relate to some
degree of civil liability. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ולמאן
דאמר שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. uleman de'amar shenei kesuvim habaim
k'echad ein melamdin. So now according to the one that says that
when two פסוקים psukim is enough or you could say for בית
שמאי Beis Shammai that has three examples, right? מעילה, what do you
call it? מעילה, טביחה ומכירה, tevicha umchira, and שליחות יד. shlichus yad.
So why do you need the ההוא? s You already know that
those are the exceptions. The rule is אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein
shaliach lidvar aveirah. Why do you need the ההוא s by שחוטי
חוץ? shchutei chutz? So
הני ההוא ההוא מאי דרש ביה? hanei hahu hahu mai darish beih?
What do you do with it? חד למעוטי שנים שאוחזין בסכין ושוחטין.
chad lema'utei shnayim she'ochazin besakin veshochetin. One to tell you that it's
only if one person does it. If two people hold the knife
and do שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, then they're not חייב כרת. chayav
kares. וחד הוא ולא אנוס הוא ולא שוגג הוא ולא מוטעה. vechad
hu velo anus hu velo shogeg hu velo mut'eh. Only if you're
doing it in your right mind and not if you're forced or
not if you're mistaken or, you know, and not if you're making
an error. You know, you're being negligent. And even though that's a
general principle, you know, that you're not חייב chayav, in those cases
when for כרת... kares... I mean שוגג shogeg you'd still be חייב
chayav. a קרבן, korban, but you're not חייב כרת. chayav kares. But
sometimes the תורה Torah tells you in particular cases as well. ואידך
מההוא ההוא. ve'idach mehahu hahu. And the other one learns out about
the cases of שוגג from the extra ה. hei. It could have
said הוא hu and it says ההוא hahu to tell you also
only in your right mind. ואידך ההוא ההוא לא דריש. ve'idach hahu
hahu lo darish. And the other says that doesn't make anything of.
Okay. So now we learn what you do with the extra ההוא
s and the principle אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shliach l'dvar aveirah.
והא דתניא. veha detanya. Now the גמרא Gemara says, that which we
taught: האומר לשלוחו צא והרוג את הנפש הוא חייב. ha'omer lishlucho tze
veharog es hanefesh hu chayav. Now you go ahead, this is really
the mafioso, the, you know, the RICO cases. Somebody goes ahead and
tells somebody go and kill somebody, commit murder. הוא חייב ומשלחו פטור.
hu chayav umshalcho patur. The murderer is חייב chayav? and the one
who sent him is exempt.
This is fascinating, in the name of חגי הנביא, Chaggai HaNavi, was
way before שמאי, Shammai, שולחו חייב. sholcho chayav. Nope, even the one
who or the one who sent him, we're going to say even
the one who sent him is חייב, chayav שנאמר: shene'emar: אותו הרגת
בחרב בני עמון. oso haragta b'cherev b'nei Amon. So because it says,
you know, when דוד David is being held accountable for the death
of אוריה החתי, Uriyah HaChiti, he's told by the נביא, Navi, you
killed him by the sword of בני עמון. b'nei Amon. Now דוד
David didn't kill him; he sent him to battle. But דוד David
is being treated as the one who killed him. So now we've
got שמאי Shammai that says that the משלח meshaleach is חייב. chayav.
And this is, you know, whatever RICO, you could execute him. Really
sounds like בדיני אדם. b'dinei adam. And maybe this would apply in
all cases, you know?
So מאי טעמא דשמאי? mai ta'ama d'Shammai? What's the reason of שמאי
הזקן? Shammai HaZaken? קסבר שני כתובים הבאים כאחד מלמדים. kasavar shnei kesuvim
habaim k'echad melamdim. It's only two cases and, you know, he doesn't—it's
like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, so he doesn't hold of that there's
a case of שליחות, yeah? There's
only two cases, right, that say יש שליח לדבר עבירה: yeish shliach
l'dvar aveirah: מעילה and טביחה ומכירה. tivichah u'michirah. And two cases serve
as the model, and we learn out from there יש שליח לדבר
עבירה. yeish shliach l'dvar aveirah. That's the rule in כל התורה כולה.
kol haTorah kullah. So the גמרא Gemara says, והוא הוא לא דריש,
v'hu hu lo darish, he doesn't learn the הוא הוא hu hu
from שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz to say only the doer. So שמאי
Shammai says the general principle is יש שליח לדבר עבירה. yeish shliach
l'dvar aveirah. Now, again, one would imagine he would say even the
משלח meshaleach is חייב, chayav, but he didn't say that. He said
the משלח meshaleach is חייב. Sounds like maybe only. And then of
course what's the question about like really? Like at what point?
דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד is a pretty also convincing, you know, point,
especially depending on the circumstances, right, about what is this person holding
over you that, you know, we should make him liable and put—make
you exempt? So maybe שמאי Shammai means they're both liable. Okay, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says, but then the גמרא Gemara is
going to—is going to give a different explanation.
The גמרא Gemara says, ואיבעית אימא לעולם דריש. v'iba'is eima l'olam darish.
No, no, no. שמאי Shammai agrees that there's no שליח shaliach לדבר
עבירה. ומאי חייב? u'mai chayav? What does שמאי Shammai mean when he
says חייב? חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. It means that you're
חייב in heaven; they'll treat you as if you're the murderer, like
the נביא Navi says to דוד, David, ואותו הרגת בחרב בני עמון.
v'oso haragta b'cherev b'nei Amon. So the גמרא says, מכלל דתנא קמא
סבר אפילו מדיני שמים נמי פטור? michlal d'Tanna Kamma savar afilu m'dinei
shamayim nami patur? Do you mean to tell me that when the
one who says that you're פטור, patur. the guy who sent somebody
to commit murder, he means that that guy, the one who sent,
like has no liability up in heaven? Is that really possible? So
אלא דיני רבה ודיני זוטא איכא בינייהו. ela dinei rabbah u'dinei zuta
ika beiniyahu. No, no, no. Everybody agrees the one who sends has
to answer for it up in heaven. The question is, is he
treated like the doer himself? According to שמאי, Shammai, down here in
human court, the murderer is put to death, is—did it, and the
one who sent is פטור. But up in heaven, they'll treat him
equally to a murderer. And as far as those who disagree with
שמאי הזקן, Shammai HaZaken, they'll treat him as somebody who, you know,
incited murder, but he won't be treated as a murderer. Okay, but
it's a difference of דיני שמים. dinei shamayim. So that's a little
bit more understandable that שמאי Shammai doesn't hold an across-the-board principle of
יש שליח לדבר עבירה. yeish shliach l'dvar aveirah. All right. Now the
גמרא says like this, אלא אדיני וביני ואיבעית אימא. ela adinei u'beini
v'iba'is eima. If you want, I could say שאני התם דגלי רחמנא
אותו הרגת בחרב בני עמון. shani hasam d'gali rachmana oso haragta b'cherev
b'nei Amon. Maybe that's a specific הלכה
by
murder. Now, again, by murder of all things, you should think by
murder, you know, דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד. Okay, but on the other
hand, it's such a weighty thing that maybe the משלח bears responsibility.
And again, especially if you say equal or additional responsibility, not in
except—not excluding from the שליח himself. So maybe by murder, yes, that's
where there'll be RICO and that's where the משלח will also be
חייב.
ואידך הרי לך כחרב בני עמון. v'idach harei l'cha k'cherev b'nei Amon.
And those who disagree with שמאי Shammai would say it's treated like
the sword of בני עמון b'nei Amon to say the opposite. מה
חרב בני עמון אי אתה נענש עליו, mah cherev b'nei Amon ee
atah ne'enash alav, the same way you're not considered to have committed,
you know, when בני עמון b'nei Amon kill people, that's not your
sin, אף אוריה החתי אי אתה נענש עליו. af Uriyah HaChiti ee
atah ne'enash alav. You're not going to be punished for the death
of אוריה החתי. Uriyah HaChiti. Completely turning the פסוק pasuk on the
head. This exact thing that is holding דוד David liable and according
to שמאי Shammai treating him ממש mamash as a murderer, you know,
for this—for those who disagree with שמאי, Shammai, it's saying no, no,
you're not held liable. Not just because you didn't do it in
your own hand, but actually it was justified. Why was it justified?
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? מורד במלכות הוה. mored b'malchus havah. Because אוריה
Uriyah was rebelling against the king's authority and therefore deserving of death,
דאמר ליה ואדוני יואב וכל עבדי אדוני על פני השדה חונים. de'amar
lei v'adoni Yoav v'chol avdei adoni al pnei hasadeh chonim. And my
master יואב Yoav and all the servants of my master are dwelling
on the—on the field, and should I go back and be with
my wife? So because he called יואב Yoav his master in the
face of דוד, David, that's giving authority to somebody other than דוד.
David.
Or the other explanation is because he was resisting דוד's David order
to go back and to be with his wife. Okay, so anyway,
what we have here is the principle אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein
shaliach lidvar aveira, There are some cases where there are, particularly when
it deals with, you know, financial civil liability. שמאי Shammai says by
murder, יש שליח לדבר עבירה, yeish shaliach lidvar aveira, the גמרא says
either he really means it as a general principle, which is amazing,
or he means it specifically by murder. Either way you would assume
he means it in addition to the one who actually did it,
or he's just talking about דיני שמים, dinei shamayim, but an equal
sin בדיני שמים. b'dinei shamayim. Okay.
Now the גמרא says like this, אמר רבא אם תמצא לומר סבר
שמאי שני כתובים באים כאחד מלמדים והוא לא דריש, Amar Rava im
timtzau lomar sabar Shammai shnei ksuvim ba'im k'echad melamdim v'hu lo darish,
if שמאי Shammai says that you learn from two פסוקים psukim from
the principles of שליח לדבר עבירה of מעילה and of טביחה ומכירה,
tvicha u'mechira, and he doesn't learn from ההוא ההוא ha'hu ha'hu to
say אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach lidvar aveira. so מודה באומר
לשלוחו צא בא על הערווה ואכול החלב, modeh b'omer l'shlucho tze ba
al ha'erva v'echol ha'chelev, there's one case, even if שמאי Shammai generally
holds יש שליח לדבר עבירה, yeish shaliach lidvar aveira, there's a category
of cases אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach lidvar aveira. And that
is if somebody says to a שליח, go ahead and have intercourse
with this woman who is a forbidden sexually, or go ahead and
eat טריף treif food. So in that case, שהוא חייב ושולחו פטור,
she'hu chayav v'sholcho patur, the doer is חייב, the sender is exempt,
שלא מצינו בכל התורה כולה זה נהנה וזה מתחייב. she'lo matzinu b'chol
ha'Torah kula ze neheneh v'ze mitchayev. We've never found in the entire
תורה Torah that one person gets הנאה hana'ah and the other person
is responsible for it. You know, those sins, another way of saying
that it's not just like it's not fair, but fundamentally the sin
there is not the act but the הנאה hana'ah experienced by the
act. So it's one thing to attribute an act to something, it's
like you killed him, it's like you stole his property, but it's
another thing that if it's about the experience of the pleasure that
is the most subjective and personal and therefore that can only be
the person who does it. It's also the principle that there's no
מתעסק בחלבים ועריות, mit'aseik b'chalavim v'arayos, exact same idea, that if somebody
says like well I was just in the middle of something else
and accidentally this happened, it's not like I did it, you can't
divorce the act from you if you were getting that הנאה hana'ah
in the doing of the act. Okay, so that's the principle of
אין שליח לדבר עבירה. איתמר. Itmar. Now we'll have one other case
here about, well, a couple others, but you know we're doing topic
by topic in שליחות and this is the question about שליח נעשה
עד. shaliach na'aseh eid.
רב אמר שליח נעשה עד. Rav amar shaliach na'aseh eid. Somebody was
sent as a שליח to marry a woman or to pay back
a debt. Can that person be an עד eid to the fact
that it occurred? You know, plus one other עד eid so you'd
have two עדים, eidim, or maybe two people were sent as a
שליח, or is he somehow considered to be like you know the
נוגע בדבר, nogei'a badavar, the same way the principal cannot do it,
the שליח you know can't be an עד eid as well. Okay,
so רב אמר שליח נעשה עד דבי רבי שילא אמרי אין שליח
נעשה עד. Rav amar shaliach na'aseh eid d'vei Rabbi Shila amri ein
shaliach na'aseh eid. It's not. מאי טעמא דבי רבי שילא? Mai ta'ama
d'vei Rabbi Shila? Why did they say not? אילם משום דלא אמר
ליה הוי לי עד הוי לי עד, Ilem meshum d'lo amar lei
havei li eid, havei li eid,
maybe because they just say it's not that there's a thing preventing
him, but making a שליח is not making an עד eid and
for somebody to serve as a witness he has to be appointed
as a witness by you know one of the parties. אלא מעתה
קידש אשה בפני שנים ולא אמר להם אתם עדי הכי נמי דלא
הוי קידושין? Ela ma'ata kideish isha bifnei shnayim v'lo amar lahem atem
eidai, hachi nami d'lo havi kiddushin? That can't be. Would you say
if somebody married a woman and didn't say to the witnesses you
be my witnesses that it wouldn't be קידושין? kiddushin. Of course it
would be קידושין. You don't need to appoint witnesses. Now of course
the funny thing is under the חופה chuppah we're always saying I'm
appointing you as my witnesses, that's also to deal with the problem
that there're also relatives there, so the relatives shouldn't ruin the witnesses
by being you know by being part of the same group of
witnesses. But anyway you do not need to designate witnesses. The only
time you need to designate witnesses is if you're admitting to something,
admitting to a debt, because then otherwise you could say oh I
was just kidding around, I wasn't being serious. But as a general
rule if witnesses are witnessing the act itself, they do not have
to be designated. So it can't be the absence of designation is
the issue.
אלא רב אמר שליח נעשה עד, Ela Rav amar shaliach na'aseh eid,
no here's the reason. רב Rav says a שליח can be an
עד. eid. אילו מי קמן אמי למילתאי, Ilu mei kaman ami l'milsai,
because by making a שליח you're just even making him like stronger.
He's going to be an עד eid and he's actually going to
be like directly involved and you know it doesn't like like it
doesn't hurt the fact that he's a שליח that he can also
testify to what happened. דבי רבי שילא אמרי אין שליח נעשה עד
כיון דאמר מר שלוחו של אדם כמותו, d'vei Rabbi Shila amri ein
shaliach na'aseh eid keivan d'amar mar shlucho shel adam k'moto, no here's
the whole problem. If he is acting as you, the same way
you can't be a witness to your own act, you need a
third party, so הוי ליה כגופיה, havi lei k'gufei, he becomes like
you and he can't be a third party. Okay, מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll
challenge this. אמר לשלושה צאו וקדשו לי אשה, Amar l'shlosha tze'u v'kadshu
li isha, we have a ברייתא, if you say to three people
go marry, go marry this woman for me, אחד שליח ושנים עדים
דברי בית שמאי. Echad shaliach u'shnayim eidim, divrei Beit Shammai. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says one of them serves as the שליח, the other
two are not the שליח and they have a separate role as
עדים. eidim. You're one or the other. You can't be both. Seems
very clearly אין שליח נעשה עד. ein shaliach na'aseh eid. What does
בית הלל Beit Hillel say? בית הלל אומרים כולם שלוחים הן. Beit
Hillel omrim kulam shluchim hen. בית הלל Beit Hillel says no, if
you said go marry, you meant all three of them are going
to be your שליח, ואין שליח נעשה עד, v'ein shaliach na'aseh eid,
and when you designated them as a שליח now they can't take
away that designation and serve as an עד eid so you're stuck,
you need to find other עדים. eidim. So whether בית הלל Beit
Hillel or בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and בית הלל Beit Hillel is
even stricter, but everybody says a שליח can't be an עד. eid.
So the גמרא says,
עד כאן לא פליגי, ad kan lo pligi, here under... but they
don't only debate אלא בשלושה *ela b'shlosha* by three, אבל בשניים *aval
b'shnayim* דברי הכל *divrei hakol* לא *lo*, everybody would agree, even בית
שמאי *Beit Shammai* would agree two wouldn't work. Obviously it didn't have
to say, it's a funny way of saying it, but the basic
point is everybody here holds אין שליח נעשה עד *ein shaliach na'aseh
ed*. So how could we say there be an opinion otherwise? How
could רב *Rav* say you could be? הוא דאמר *hu d'amar*, no
רב *Rav* says כי האי תנא *ki hai tanna* like the following
תנא *tanna*, דתניא *d'tanya* רבי נתן אומר *Rabbi Natan omer* בית שמאי
אומרים *Beit Shammai omrim* שליח ועד אחד *shaliach v'ed echad* בית הלל
אומרים
*Beit Hillel omrim* שליח ושני עדים *shaliach u'shnei eidim*. So there's a
ברייתא *baraita* where בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says actually two is enough,
you can have a שליח *shaliach* and one other עד *ed* and
they make the two עדים *eidim* for let's say קידושין *kiddushin*, the
שליח *shaliach* plus one person. And בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says a
שליח *shaliach* you have to do two other people. The שליח *shaliach*
can't be an עד *ed*. But at least בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*
says a שליח *shaliach* can be an עד *ed*. The גמרא *Gemara*
says ורב כי בית שמאי *v'Rav
ki Beit Shammai*? Wait, so that doesn't work, רב *Rav* is going,
why would רב *Rav* go like בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*? We don't
rule like בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says איפכא
*ipech*, reverse it. According to that teaching of רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*,
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* is the one that says that a שליח
*shaliach* cannot be an עד *ed* and בית הלל *Beit Hillel* is
the one that says a שליח *shaliach* can be an עד *ed*.
So all of the evidence sounds like a שליח *shaliach* cannot be
an עד *ed*. We're really forcing this position that a שליח *shaliach*
can be an עד *ed*, but in the end that is the
way we rule that a שליח *shaliach* can be an עד *ed*.
רב אחא בריה דרבא מתני איפכא *Rav Acha brei d'Rava matni ipech*.
Okay, and רב אחא בריה דרבא *Rav Acha brei d'Rava* teaches the
debate of רב *Rav* and the בי שילא *Be Shila* the opposite.
רב אמר *Rav amar* אין שליח נעשה עד *ein shaliach na'aseh ed*,
it doesn't work. בי שילא אמרי *Be Shila amri* שליח נעשה עד
*shaliach na'aseh ed*, it does work. והלכתא *v'hilcheta* the הלכה *halacha* is
שליח נעשה עד *shaliach na'aseh ed*. It does work even though it's
very forced in terms of the earlier תנאים *tannaim*. אמר רבא אמר
רב נחמן *Amar Rava amar Rav Nachman* אמר לשניים צאו וקדשו לי
אשה *amar l'shnayim tze'u v'kadshu li isha* הן שלוחיו והן עדיו *hen
shluchav v'hen eidav*. Now we're going to have פסק *psak* that's based
on this principle of שליח נעשה עד *shaliach na'aseh ed*. If you
say to two people go marry me this woman, they are the
שלוחים *shluchim* and they both can be the עדים *eidim* to the
event. וכן בגירושין *v'chen b'gerushin* the same is true בגירושין *b'gerushin* top
of מ"ג עמוד ב' *mem gimmel amud bet*. וכן בדיני ממונות *v'chen
b'dinei mamonot* the same is true by monetary matters if you want
to pay back a debt. The same people that are the שלוחים
*shluchim* to pay it back can be the עדים *eidim* that it
took place. וצריכא *u'tzricha* and you need to tell me all three
cases. דאי אשמעינן בקידושין *d'i ashmi'inan b'kiddushin* had you just said קידושין
*kiddushin* משום דלאיסורא קאתי *mishum d'l'misrei kasi* because you're making the concern
is is that if this guy is getting involved and he's being
the שליח *shaliach*
maybe he'll have some vested interest in this and there'll be some
reason that he won't be totally honest as an עד *ed*. Okay
so by קידושין *kiddushin* this woman even if the woman catches his
eye by saying that she got married it makes her forbidden to
him. So there's no concern of any נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar*. So
now we've moved off from a formal idea that you are considered
like the party itself, שליח *shaliach* in principle נעשה עד *na'aseh ed*,
but nevertheless we're introducing concerns that maybe sometimes you'd be considered נוגע
בדבר *nogea b'davar*. Okay but in the קידושין *kiddushin* what could the
נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar* be? אבל גירושין ניחוש שמא עיניו נתן בה
*aval gerushin neichosh shema einav natan ba* but by גירושין *gerushin* maybe
he wants to marry her. Now of course what's the big deal,
you know, give the גט *get* and then say you gave it.
What's where's the נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar*? But maybe he'll feel like
look, you know, because he got involved this woman caught his eye
and he decided he wanted to marry her and then maybe even
if something happened I don't know the גט *get* got lost he's
still going to say it. So maybe his involvement could make him
a degree of a נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar* and we wouldn't trust
his testimony. ואי אשמעינן גירושין משום דאיתא לבי תרי לא חזי *v'i
ashmi'inan gerushin mishum d'ita l'bei trai lo chazi*. And if it said
גירושין *gerushin* we okay but you know what? You need two witnesses
to say that she was divorced and they're both saying she's divorced.
So we're not concerned of נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar* because she can't
marry both of them. They can't both be נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar*.
אבל ממונא אימא הני מפלג פליגי *aval mamona eima hanei miflag palig*
but by money maybe again both of them will say hey let's
keep the money to ourselves and we'll split it and we'll say
we paid it back. Okay so therefore once they're getting involved maybe
they become a bit of נוגע בדבר *nogea b'davar* and you can't
trust their testimony. So צריכי *tzrichi* it tells you you can at
the end of the day it's two witnesses. Just because they were
also sent to deliver the money doesn't mean that you don't believe
them that they did it. Although you are wondering especially in the
money case, you know, they're on their way to deliver the money
they decide to pocket it they decide whatever but they at the
end of the day there's no formal problem and witnesses are witnesses
so we say שליח *shaliach* is נעשה עד *na'aseh ed*. Okay now
מאי קסבר אי קסבר המלוה את חבירו בעדים צריך לפורעו בעדים הני
נוגעין בעדות נינהו *mai kasavar i kasavar hamalveh et chaveiro b'eidim tzarich
l'faro b'eidim hanei nogein b'eidus ninhu*. Now the גמרא *Gemara* says wait
a minute there is a נוגע בעדות *nogea b'eidus* because they were
sent they were given the $100 to pay this guy back. Now
if they say that they paid him
then that let's say that you know what's their responsibility to the
guy who sent them? That guy who sent them gave them money
and now he's going to say and let's say they and let's
say this guy they were to say, you know, we you know
we didn't give the money to the guy you said but we
gave it back to you. And he said you never gave it
back to me. So that's the question of המלוה את חבירו בעדים
*malveh et chaveiro b'eidim* although here it's פיקדון *pikadon* do you need
would they be believed to say they gave it back to the
משלח *meshaleach*. So if the הלכה *halacha* is they would not be
believed to say they gave it back to the משלח *meshaleach*... then
they're נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus* because by testifying that they gave it
to the creditor, they're getting themselves out of liability to the משלח
*meshaleiach*. If they acknowledge that they didn't give it to the creditor,
then they would have to pay it to the משלח *meshaleiach* and
they wouldn't be believed to say that they had paid it back
to the משלח *meshaleiach*. So their testimony that they had done their
שליחות *shlichus* and paid the creditor gets them out of a responsibility
of to the משלח *meshaleiach* because other because they would not be
believed to say that they had given it back. So therefore, therefore
they cannot testify because they're נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus*, they gain by
testifying that it was given to the creditor. אלא לעולם קסבר *Ella
le-olam kasavar*, you got the מלווה את חבירו בעדים *malveh את chaveiro
be-eidim*, הני נוגע בעדות נינהו *hani nogeia be-eidus ninhu*. דאי אמרי לא
פרענא *De-ei amri lo para'na*, if they admit they didn't give it
to the creditor, אמר ליה פרעוני *amar leih par'uni*, he would say,
okay, give it back to me. And they wouldn't be believed to
say that they had given it back to him. אלא לעולם קסבר
מלווה את חבירו בעדים אין צריך לפורעו בעדים *Ella le-olam kasavar malveh
es chaveiro be-eidim ein tzarich le-far'o be-eidim*. Ah, so they would not
have to bring witnesses to say they had given the money back
to the משלח *meshaleiach*. So because if you lend money with עדים
*eidim* as opposed to a שטר *shtar*, a שטר *shtar* you always
need evidence that you paid it back. But here if the money
was given to the שלוחים *shluchim* with עדים *eidim* and not a
שטר *shtar* and the שלוחים *shluchim* would be believed to say we
didn't give it to the creditor and we gave it back to
you, if they would just totally be believed on their word, so
מלווה את חבירו בעדים אין צריך לפורעו בעדים *malveh es chaveiro be-eidim
ein tzarich le-far'o be-eidim*, then they have nothing to gain by lying
to say they paid the creditor. If they wanted to lie, they
could just as easily have said, we gave it back to you
the משלח *meshaleiach*. So since they could just as they're believed when
they say they gave it back to the משלח *meshaleiach*, they're not
נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus* and they have nothing to gain by lying
and therefore their עדות *eidus* works to say they paid the creditor.
Okay. ומיגו דמצי למימר הדרינהו ללווה *U-migu de-maci le-meimar hadreinhu le-loveh*, since
they could say they gave it back to the משלח *meshaleiach* and
they would be believed because מלווה את חבירו בעדים *malveh es chaveiro
be-eidim*, if you lend money with witnesses you don't have to pay
it back with witnesses, יכולים למימר פרענא למלווה *yekholim le-meimar para'na le-malveh*,
they're believed to say we paid the מלווה *malveh*. Now this is
not a normal מיגו *migu*. They're believed to say they paid the
מלווה *malveh* because they're עדים *eidim* and עדים *eidim* are believed to
say that the מלווה *malveh* was paid. But it just means they're
not נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus*, they don't gain, they're not considered to
have an interest and that they stand to gain from their testimony.
There's nothing they stand to gain from their testimony because they would
totally be believed to say they paid back the לווה *loveh*. All
right.
והשתא דתיקון רבנן שבועת היסת *Ve-hashta de-tikkun rabanan shevuas hesess*, now that
the rabbis established the principle of a שבועת היסת *shevuas hesess*, which
means that you always pretty much have to make a שבועה *shevua*
when somebody makes a claim against you, certainly if it's a טענת
ברי *tainas bari*. So now they do have to gain because if
they say they paid the creditor,
they're off the hook. But if they say they didn't pay the
creditor and the מלווה *malveh* says then give me my money, if
they were to say we gave it to you, they would have
to make a שבועה *shevua*. So by saying they paid the creditor,
they're freeing themselves from making a שבועה *shevua* to the מלווה *malveh*.
So they are no longer believed to say that they paid the
creditor because they would, I'm sorry, שבועה *shevua* to the לווה
*loveh*. So now that they said שבועת היסת *shevuas hesess*, משתבעי הני
עדים דיהבינהו ליה *mishtbaei hani eidim di-yehavinu lei*, so the witnesses take
an oath that they paid the creditor, okay, their עדות *eidus* is
not believed because they're נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus*, but they're taking an
oath that they paid the creditor. ומשתבע מלווה דלא שקיל *u-mishtba malveh
de-lo shakil*, and the מלווה *malveh* takes an oath and he says,
I never got it from them, ופרע
לווה למלווה *u-fara loveh le-malveh*, and then the לווה *loveh* has to
pay the מלווה *malveh* and the לווה *loveh* is out the money
he gave. So it's ironic but you know but and that but
since once they become נוגע בעדות *nogeia be-eidus* because they have a
שבועה *shevua* responsibility to the לווה *loveh* and they gain by testifying,
they no longer can serve as witnesses. So now you they can't
serve as witnesses, so they say, we paid, so he says you
know so the guy who gave them the money is saying but
the guy's saying he didn't get the money but they're saying but
we paid. So basically that's a classic case of making a claim,
no evidence, etc., so they make a שבועה *shevua* that they did
do what they said they did pay. The מלווה *malveh* makes a
שבועה *shevua* that he didn't and then the לווה *loveh* still owes
the money to the מלווה *malveh*. So it's very unfair to the
לווה *loveh*, especially because it was only their שבועה *shevua* obligation to
the לווה *loveh* that undermined their ability to serve as witnesses and
to say that they actually paid the debt. But that is the
way that works out. Okay, so that was a little bit of
a digression but that's all part of the discussion of שליח נעשה
עד *shaliach naaseh eid*.